Finding aid for the L.A. Rebellion Collection LSC.2429
UCLA Library Special Collections
L.A. Rebellion collection
1972-2009
UCLA Library Special Collections
Clark, Larry, 1948-
Dash, Julie
LSC.2429
10 linear feet (12 boxes, 3 flat boxes, 1 half box, 1 oversized folder)
30 linear feet Unprocessed (26 record cartons, 1 flat box, 2 tubes)
214 audiovisual carriers (214 audiocassettes)
13 born-digital carriers (13 floppy disks)
As part of an effort to desegregate the UCLA School of Theater, Film, and Television in the late 1960s, a group of African and African-American students enrolled as part of an Ethno-Communications program. Here, these students gained access to the equipment and instruction needed in order to tell their stories. For approximately two decades, these students created a new type of cinema that would later be known as the L.A. Rebellion. These filmmakers represent an early effort to create a new and alternative practice of Black Cinema in the United States. Processed materials consist of the papers of L.A. Rebellion filmmakers Larry Clark and Julie Dash.
Conditions Governing Access
Portions of collection unprocessed. Material in the Larry Clark papers and Julie Dash papers are processed. Please see LSC's Access to Unprocessed Collections Policy for more information about levels of discovery and access of special collections materials and registering interest in unprocessed collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Larry Clark papers, gift of Larry Clark, 2019. Julie Dash papers, gift of Julie Dash, 2016.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9996859204406533
Biographical / Historical
As part of an effort to desegregate the UCLA School of Theater, Film, and Television in the late 1960s, a group of African and African-American students enrolled as part of an Ethno-Communications program. Here, these students gained access to the equipment and instruction needed in order to tell their stories. For approximately two decades, these students created a new type of cinema that would later be known as the L.A. Rebellion. Some of these filmmakers include Charles Burnett, Larry Clark, and Julie Dash. These filmmakers represent an early effort to create a new and alternative practice of Black Cinema in the United States. These films have received substantial recognition on the international festival stage as well as in commercial markets.
Clark, Larry. L.A. Rebellion Oral Histories: Larry Clark. By Dr. Jacqueline Stewart and Dr. Christopher Horak. June 2, 2010.
L.A. Rebellion: Creating a New Black Cinema. UCLA Library Film and Television Archive. Accessed July 6, 2022. https://www.cinema.ucla.edu/la-rebellion/la-rebellion-creating-new-black-cinema.
Scope and Contents
The L.A. Rebellion collection currently contains the papers of LA Rebellion filmmakers Larry Clark and Julie Dash who are both known for their writing and directing.
Larry Clark's papers, which comprise the first series of this collection, primarily focus on his 1977 film Passing Through. The film traveled internationally at film festivals for decades following its release, and these files contain a significant amount of ephemera from those festivals. These papers also contain press clippings and promotional materials from both the United States and internationally about Passing Through. This series also contains correspondence to Clark, photographs, and film strips from his films Passing Through and As Above, So Below (1973).
The second series within the LA Rebellion collection contains the papers of LA Rebellion filmmaker Julie Dash. They primarily focus on her 1991 film Daughters of the Dust though the collection does contain some materials for Diary of an African Nun (1977) and Illusions (1982). This collection contains a significant number of press clippings about Dash and her works, from both the United States and international news sources. These papers also contain flyers, brochures, and other ephemera from the many film festivals (both within and outside of the United States) and screenings that showcased Dash's films. This series also contains information about awards won by Dash, critical writings by others about her films, information about the production process for her films including screenplays, and additional ephemera and correspondence relating to Dash and her works.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in the following series:
Series 1: Larry Clark papers, 1972-2008
Subseries 1.1: Festival materials, 1973-2005
Subseries 1.2: Passing Through promotional materials and press, 1972-2008
Subseries 1.3: Photographs, film strips, ephemera, 1973-2006
Series 2: Julie Dash papers, 1972-2009
Subseries 2.1: Press clippings, 1977-2000
Subseries 2.2: Film festival and screening materials, 1978-2009
Subseries 2.3: Film production materials and screenplays, 1979-2002
Subseries 2.4: Awards and critical writing, 1980-2009
Subseries 2.5: Correspondence, film catalogs, and ephemera, 1972-2009
Related Materials
Related Materials
Horace Tapscott papers (PASC-M.0237)
Horace Tapscott papers (PASC-M.0237). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
LA Rebellion: Larry Clark oral history interview
LA Rebellion: Larry Clark oral history interview. Interview of Larry Clark [oral history transcript] / Jan-Christopher Horak and Jacqueline Stewart, interviewers. UCLA Library Special Collections, Center for Oral History Research interview, 2010. Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
As Above, So Below (1972)
As Above, So Below (1972). Available at UCLA Film and Television Archive Research and Study Center, Powell Library, UCLA.
Cutting Horse (2002)
Cutting Horse (2002). Available at UCLA Film and Television Archive Research and Study Center, Powell Library, UCLA.
Passing Through (1977)
Passing Through (1977). Available at UCLA Film and Television Archive Research and Study Center, Powell Library, UCLA.
Tamu (1970)
Tamu (1970). Available at UCLA Film and Television Archive Research and Study Center, Powell Library, UCLA.
LA Rebellion: Julie Dash oral history interview.
Interview of Julie Dash (oral history transcript) / Allyson Field, Jan-Christopher Horak, and Jacqueline Stewart, interviewers. UCLA Library Special Collections, Center for Oral History Research interview, 2010. Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Four Women (1975)
Four Women (1975). Available at UCLA Film and Television Archive Research and Study Center, Powell Library, UCLA.
The Diary of an African Nun (1977)
The Diary of an African Nun (1977). Available at UCLA Film and Television Archive Research and Study Center, Powell Library, UCLA.
Illusions (1982)
Illusions (1982). Available at UCLA Film and Television Archive Research and Study Center, Powell Library, UCLA.
Daughters of the Dust (1991)
Daughters of the Dust (1991). Available at UCLA Film and Television Archive Research and Study Center, Powell Library, UCLA.
Funny Valentines (1999)
Funny Valentines (1999). Available at UCLA Film and Television Archive Research and Study Center, Powell Library, UCLA.
The Rosa Parks Story (2001)
The Rosa Parks Story (2001). Available at UCLA Film and Television Archive Research and Study Center, Powell Library, UCLA.
L.A. Rebellion; African American motion picture producers and directors; Independent filmmakers -- California -- Los Angeles; Independent films -- California -- Los Angeles; Experimental films -- California -- Los Angeles; Clark, Larry, 1948- -- Archives; Dash, Julie -- Archives
- Series 1: Larry Clark papers, 1972-2008
  Biographical / Historical
  Larry Clark (b. 1948), now retired, was a filmmaker and professor of film at San Francisco State University. He is best known for his UCLA M.F.A. thesis film, Passing Through (1977), which is widely regarded as one of the greatest jazz movies ever made. Clark now resides in the Bay Area and works as a painter.
  "L.A. Rebellion: Larry Clark." UCLA Library Film and Television Archive. Accessed October 12, 2022. https://www.cinema.ucla.edu/la-rebellion/larry-clark.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the papers of L.A. Rebellion filmmaker Larry Clark, and they primarily focus on his 1977 film Passing Through. The film traveled internationally at film festivals for decades following its release, and these files contain a significant amount of ephemera from those festivals. These papers also contain press clippings and promotional materials from both the United States and internationally about Passing Through. This series also contains correspondence to Clark, photographs, and film strips from his films Passing Through and As Above, So Below (1973).
  Arrangement
  Materials were arranged based on the existing order. Materials were then arranged and organized into three subseries, covering film festival materials and ephemera, promotional materials and press about Passing Through (1977), and other photographs, film strips and ephemera related to Larry Clark, Cutting Horse (2002), and awards given to Clark.
  - Subseries 1.1: Festival materials, 1973-2005
    This subseries contains materials related to film festivals and screenings that featured Passing Through from 1977-2005. This includes posters, brochures, pins, Clark's identification badges, and other ephemera.
    - Clark festival badges, 1981-2003 (Box 9)
    - Festival pins and buttons, 1987-1988 (Box 9)
    - Festival posters and ephemera, 1979-1996 (Box 8)
    - U.S.S.R. festival ephemera, 1987-1988 (Box 9)
    - Festival ephemera, 1979-1991 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - French festival ephemera, 1981-2000 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - French festival ephemera, 1985-1998 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - French festival ephemera, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - French festival correspondence to Clark, 1981-2000 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Cannes 1999 ephemera (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
    - Cannes 1999 correspondence (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - American festival ephemera, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - American festival ephemera, 2000-2005 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - American festival ephemera, 1983-1994 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - American festival ephemera, 1973-1981 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - International festival ephemera, 1977-1987 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - International festival ephemera, 1991-1996 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - International festival ephemera, 1985-1991 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Burkina Faso festivals, 1983-1987 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Algeria festival 1987 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Mozambique festival, New Orleans festival, 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - India festival 1984 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Holland festival 1981 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - 1980 Paris (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Festival at the Lake (Berkeley, CA), 1996 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - London film festival, 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - VII International Festival of New Latin American Cinema (Havana, Cuba), 1985 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - U.S.S.R. (Uzbekistan) festival ephemera, 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Italian festival ephemera and correspondence, 1984-1989 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - United Kingdom festivals ephemera and correspondence, 1978-1982 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Black American Film Festival, Amsterdam; press, correspondence, ephemera, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Festival ephemera and correspondence (Germany, Spain, Martinique, Canada, India, Nigeria), 1975-1998 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Mogadishu, Somalia festival ephemera and correspondence, 1981-1985 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Burkina Faso festival ephemera, 1979-1985 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - International Festival of Women and Cinema, Guadeloupe, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Algeria film festival, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Festival de Cinema des Noires Americains, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - 8me Festival de Cinema des Minorities Nationales, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Subseries 1.2: Passing Through promotional materials and press, 1972-2008
    This subseries contains promotional materials and press concerning Passing Through. This includes original newspaper clippings, photocopied newspaper clippings, critical writings, still photos from production, and the film's dialogue list.
    - Press reviews, foreign, 1977-1981 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Passing Through press, 1979-2008 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Passing Through press, festival ephemera, 1985-1996 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Passing Through press, 1977-1986 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Passing Through press, 1977-2008 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Passing Through press: Burkina Faso, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Passing Through press, 1977-1996 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Passing Through press, 1980s (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Press about Passing Through, 1980s (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Passing Through press, 1980s-1990s (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Press and correspondence to Clark, 1973-2000s (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Passing Through correspondence and press, 1975-1986 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Passing Through screening ephemera, press, correspondence to Clark, 1980-1996 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence to Clark about Passing Through, 1977-1990s (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Critical writing on Passing Through, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Critical writing on Passing Through, 1981-1993 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Film magazines discussing Passing Through, 1983-2001 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Passing Through P.R. originals, 1977-1986 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Passing Through dialogue list, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 1.3: Photographs, film strips, ephemera, 1973-2006
    This subseries contains photographs, film strips, and ephemera related to Larry Clark and the films he directed, including Cutting Horse (2002) and As Above, So Below (1972). It includes awards that were given to Clark, correspondence to Clark showcasing interest in screening his films, and correspondence surrounding his never-produced film Red Sand, Black Roses.
    - Production still photos of Passing Through, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Photos: Passing Through, As Above, So Below, Larry Clark, 1972-2001 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Passing Through still photos, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Red Sand, Black Roses correspondence, 1989-1994 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Clark personal copy As Above, So Below book, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Writings that reference Clark, 1980-2006 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Rockefeller Foundation fellowship award, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Rockefeller Foundation fellowship award, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Clark awards and recognition, 1979-1997 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence with Clark, 1978-1999 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Burkina Faso film school, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - U.S.S.R., Moscow, Sochi photos, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Press about Cutting Horse, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence to Clark, 1974-1979 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence to Clark, 1973-2000 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Cutting Horse ephemera, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Unlabeled photos, Clarence Muse interview, Kathleen Conwell Collins Prettyman memorial card, used Cuban target practice cards, 1976-1988; undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Series 2: Julie Dash papers, 1972-2009
  Julie Dash (b. 1952) is a filmmaker who completed her M.F.A. at UCLA in 1985. She became the first Black woman to direct a feature film that would receive a general theatrical release in the United States with her 1991 film Daughters of the Dust. When she isn't creating films, she can often be found lecturing at universities across the United States.
  "L.A. Rebellion: Julie Dash." UCLA Library Film and Television Archive. Accessed October 12, 2022. https://www.cinema.ucla.edu/la-rebellion/julie-dash.
  This series contains the papers of L.A. Rebellion filmmaker Julie Dash. They primarily focus on her 1991 film Daughters of the Dust, though the collection does contain some materials for Diary of an African Nun (1977) and Illusions (1982). This series contains a significant number of press clippings about Dash and her works, from both American and international news sources. These papers also contain flyers, brochures, and other ephemera from the many film festivals (both within and outside of the United States) and screenings that showcased Dash's films. This series also contains information about awards won by Dash, critical writings by others about her films, information about the production process for her films including screenplays, correspondence, and additional ephemera relating to Dash and her works.
  Materials were arranged based primarily on the existing order. Materials were then intellectually arranged into five subseries. The subseries cover press, film festival materials, film production materials, awards and critical writings, and additional ephemera including correspondence to Dash.
  - Subseries 2.1: Press clippings, 1977-2000
    This subseries contains press clippings that relate to Julie Dash and her films, with the majority of the press clippings covering Daughters of the Dust (1991). It includes press from American news sources as well as international news sources. It includes original newspaper clippings, newspaper clippings that had been photocopied, and magazine clippings.
    Materials in this subseries have been arranged with materials related to Dash's smaller films highlighted first, followed by materials related to Daughters of the Dust (1991).
    - Diary of an African Nun press, 1977 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Diary of an African Nun press, 1977-1982 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Illusions press and promotional material, 1982-1985 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Incognito press & advertisement, 1999 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Daughters of the Dust novel press, 1992-1998 (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - Daughters of the Dust press, 1989-1993 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Daughters of the Dust press, 1990 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Daughters of the Dust American press, 1991-1992 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - United States press (Daughters of the Dust), 1990-1999 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Mother Jones (Daughters of the Dust), 1990 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - NBPC Newsletter (Daughters of the Dust), 1991 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Dallas Morning News (Daughters of the Dust), 1992 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - New York Press (Daughters of the Dust), 1992 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Eight Rock Magazine (Daughters of the Dust), 1990 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Elle Magazine (Daughters of the Dust), 1989 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - The Hollywood Reporter (Daughters of the Dust), 1991-1992 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Essence Magazine (Daughters of the Dust), 1991 (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - Emerge Magazine (Daughters of the Dust), 1990 (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Boston Phoenix (Daughters of the Dust), 1992 (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - American Visions (Daughters of the Dust), 1991 (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - The Post-Courier (Daughters of the Dust), 1989 (Box 16, Folder 17)
    - San Francisco Weekly (Daughters of the Dust), 1992 (Box 16, Folder 20)
    - The Village Voice (Daughters of the Dust), 1991-1992 (Box 16, Folder 21)
    - Montage (Daughters of the Dust), undated (Box 16, Folder 22)
    - The Independent (Daughters of the Dust), 1991 (Box 16, Folder 23)
    - Japanese press on Dash, 1990 (Box 16, Folder 18)
    - International press, 1985-1993 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - United States press, 1988-1998 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - United States press, 1989-1997 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Film magazines referencing Dash, 1986-1994 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Film magazines referencing Dash, 1980-1999 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Film magazines referencing Dash, 1986-2000 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Press referencing Dash and other Black filmmakers, 1980-1993 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Press referencing Dash and other Black filmmakers, 1983-1990 (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Subseries 2.2: Film festival and screening materials, 1978-2009
    This subseries contains materials related to film festivals and screenings, including the 1991 Sundance Film Festival and the 1991 Toronto International Film Festival, that featured Dash's films from 1978 to 2009. These materials include flyers, brochures, and advertising materials for these events.
    - Film festival programs (San Francisco, New York, Miami), 1978-1997 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Cannes "New Black American Shorts" flyers, 1980 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Festival flyers and brochures, 1980-1981 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Film festivals and screenings brochures, 1980-1998 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Film festival brochures and ephemera, 1980-2009 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Film festival programs, 1981-1993 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Film festival flyers and brochures, 1982-2003 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Film screenings information, 1982-2004 (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - Event flyers and posters, 1983-1999 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Film festival programs, 1984-1991 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Film festivals and screenings, 1987-2009 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Film festival programs (Tokyo, Torino), 1988-1993 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Film festival brochure (Toronto International Film Festival), 1991 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Film festival brochure (Munich), 1991 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Film festival program (Toronto International Film Festival), 1991 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Blacklight Film Festival press information, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Sundance Film Festival press release, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 19)
    - "American Playhouse" event paperwork, 1993 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - "The Rosa Parks Story" premiere information, 2002 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Subseries 2.3: Film production materials and screenplays, 1979-1992
    This subseries contains materials related to the production of Dash's films, with the majority of the materials relating to Daughters of the Dust (1991) and Illusions (1982). It includes screenplays, production details, music cue sheets, and promotional materials for the films.
    - Illusions screenplay (French translation), 1979 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Illusions screenplay, music cue sheet, promotional card, undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Handwritten notes on Illusions stock footage, 1981 (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - Illusions royalties information, production details, press clippings, 1981-1991 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Illusions final script, 1982 (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - Illusions promotional materials, undated (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Daughters of the Dust annotated screenplay, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Daughters of the Dust location list, press book, 1989-1991 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Daughters of the Dust promotional material, undated (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Daughters of the Dust & Diary of an African Nun production still photos, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Praise House screenplay, 1991 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Lost in the Night screenplay, 1992 (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Subseries 2.4: Awards and critical writing, 1980-2009
    This subseries contains documents related to awards Julie Dash has won as well as critical writing about her works. It includes awards event programs, fellowship award letters, published essays about her works, and student writings about her works.
    - Awards programs, 1981-1993 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Awards and fellowship letters, 1983-2003 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Awards program brochures, 1991-2009 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Awards ceremony brochures, 1992-2003 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Awards ceremony brochures, 1992-2003 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Awards festival programs, 1993-2002 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Critical essay on Gullah and Geechee women, 1980 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Critical writings on Dash's works, 1989-2009 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Critical writing on Daughters of the Dust, 1991-2003 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Critical essay on Daughters of the Dust, 1993 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 2.5: Correspondence, film catalogs, and ephemera, 1972-2009